Guide to the James C. King papers, 1837-1968 MS0748.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
James C. King papers
1837-1968
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS0748.UA
3.5 Linear Feet
Collection includes books, videotapes, research notes, and correspondence of Dr. James King, professor of German. They range in date from 1837-1961.
Acquisition Information
Acquired through donations of James King, in 1999 and 2002.
Biographical Note
James C. King earned his B.A. (1949), M.A. (1950), and Ph.D. (1954) from The George Washington University and is Professor Emeritus of German. As a student he was prepared in linguistics by Professor Edward H. Sehrt, who taught at GW from 1925-1953, serving as Professor of German and Chairman of the Germanic Languages and Literature Department.
After teaching French, German, and Latin at the St. Albans School for Boys in Washington, Professor King joined the faculty of GW in 1955. He became Professor Emeritus in 1991. In 1960-1961 he collaborated with Siegfried H. Muller of Adelphi University in establishing and directing the Languages-of-the-World Archives under a contract with the U.S. Office of Education. In 1962 Professor King was appointed deputy member of the Committee on International Exchange of Persons.
He also represented the American Council of Learned Societies in selecting American scholars for lectureships and research opportunities abroad under the Fulbright-Hays Program. In the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences Professor King directed research on Old High German language and literature, and the linguistic analysis of modern German.
Professor King belonged to the American Goethe Society, Linguistic Society of America, and the Mediaeval Academy of America. He served as the first president of the D.C. Chapter of the American Association of Teachers of German (1959-61). From 1964-66 he was president of GW's Chapter of Phi Beta Kappa.
After retirement, Professor King donated the official two millionth volume to the Gelman Library in 2001. The volume, An Illustrated Atlas; Geographical, Statistical, and Historical, of the United States, and the Adjacent Countries by T.G. Bradford dates from 1838 and shows the individual states, territories, and major cities of the United States, with maps of Canada and the West Indies.
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include books, videotapes, research notes, and correspondence. They range in date from 1837-1961 and were donated to the University Archives in two accessions by James C. King in 1999 and 2002.
Collection Organization
Organized in three series: Books, St. Gall videotapes, Edward Sehrt materials.
Collection note
Books not written by James King have been separated from the collection and cataloged (Special Collections stacks).
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Maps; Historical maps; Washington (D.C.); German Languages; George Washington University. Graduate School of Arts and Sciences; American Association of Teachers of German; George Washington University--Alumni and alumnae; King, James Cecil; George Washington University; Sehrt, Edward Henry
- Books, 1961-2002; MS0748 Series 1; 1 Linear foot (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Materials in this series include books and articles written by James King. They range in date from 1961-2002, and were donated to the University Archives in 2002.
  - Peter Hat Pech, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Culture of the Abbey of St. Gall: an overview, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sangallensia in Washington: The arts and letters in Medieval and Broque St. Gall, viewed from the late twentieth century, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous brochures, 1974-2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous brochures, 1975-2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- St. Gall videos, 1996; MS0748 Series 2; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 2)
  Materials in this series include videotapes on St. Gall and were donated to the University Archives in 1999.
  - Der Kloster Sankt Gallen, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Abbey of Saint Gall, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Edward Sehrt materials, 1837-1968; MS0748 Series 3; 2 Linear feet (Box 4, Box 3)
  Materials in this series books, articles, notes, and correspondence by Edward Sehrt, Professor of German at GW. They were donated to University Archives in 2002.
  - Mimeographs and notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Scholarly articles, reprints, 1926-1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Handwritten notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Notes on Notker Concordance, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Notes on Notker- Praetentium Germaneum, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Notes on Notker- Psalms, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Notker- list of suffixal elements, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Scholarly articles, reprints, 1939-1956 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Books from the library of Edward Sehrt, 1876-1958 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Reviews, 1944-1953 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Scholarly articles, reprints, 1837-1961 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Scholarly articles, reprints, 1876-1934 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Notes, correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Scholarly articles, reprints, 1942-1953 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Scholarly articles, reprints, 1928-1955 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Mimeographed copy of manuscript, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Germanistischen Feiertags, 1913 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Schriften zur Germanischen Phililogie, 1889 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Ubersetzung und Erlauterung, 1837 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Die Flexionslehre in Notkers Althochdeutscher Ubersetzung, 1886 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Beitrage zur Syntax des Notker'schen Boethius: Inaugural-Dissertation, 1883 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Notkers des Deutschen Werke, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Vollstandiges Worterbuch zum Heliand und zur Altsachsischen Genesis, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Ubersetzung und Erlauterung, 1837 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Germanic Studies in honor of Edward Henry Sehrt, 04/03/1968 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Studies in honor of Hermann Collitz, presented by a group of his pupils and friends on the occasion of his seventy-fifth birthday, February 4, 1930, 02/04/1930 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Wortschatz und Sprachformen der Wiener Notker-Handschrift, 1875 (Box 4, Folder 11)